<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, aldermen and citizens of the city of London, in the parish church of S. Mary le Bow, September 3, 1683 being the day of humiliation for the late dreadfull fire / by William Hopkins ...</title>
            <author>Hopkins, William, 1647-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17537</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12865851</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12865851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94731</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94731)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 384:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, aldermen and citizens of the city of London, in the parish church of S. Mary le Bow, September 3, 1683 being the day of humiliation for the late dreadfull fire / by William Hopkins ...</title>
                  <author>Hopkins, William, 1647-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John V, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:94731:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Pritchard Mayor, Jovis,</hi> ſexto die <hi>Septembr. 1683.</hi> Annóque Regni Regis <hi>Caroli</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi <hi>Angliae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>XXXV<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> to print his Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before the Lord Mayor and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Citizens of this City, at <hi>Bow-Church,</hi> on <hi>Monday</hi> laſt, being the day of Humiliation for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Fire, <hi>anno</hi> 1666.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagstaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94731:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the <hi>RIGHT HONOURABLE</hi> THE LORD MAYOR, Aldermen and Citizens Of the CITY of <hi>LONDON,</hi> In the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Mary le Bow, September</hi> 3. 1683.</p>
            <p>Being the day of Humiliation for the late DREADFULL FIRE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Hopkins,</hi> B.D. and Prebendary of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezra, IX. 13, 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And after all this is come upon us for our evil deeds, and for our great treſpaſs; ſeeing that thou, our God, haſt puniſhed us leſs than our iniquities deſerve, and haſt given us ſuch DELIVERANCE AS THIS:</p>
               <p>Should we again break thy commandments— Wouldſt thou not be angry with us till thou hadſt conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant nor eſcaping?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94731:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94731:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir <hi>WILLIAM PRITCHARD,</hi> LORD MAYOR Of the CITY of <hi>LONDON,</hi> AND TO THE HONOURABLE COURT of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am ſufficiently conſcious that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this plain Diſcourſe, but the honeſt deſign it proſecutes, worthy of that acceptance it found with the Honourable Audience before whom it was preached. Nevertheleſs, ſince it's your Lordſhip's pleaſure, that I ſhould make it more publick than I ever deſigned, I dare not diſpute your commands or doubt your Patronage. I am ſure I need it in a high degree, whether I conſider the weakneſs of the diſcourſe it ſelf, or into what an ill-natured and cenſorious World it adventures. But I am little concerned what reception will be given it by curious and criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb facs="tcp:94731:3"/>
Readers, who reade and hear Sermons, as they do Plays, merely for entertainment, and to ſhew what Judges they are. I was not ſo ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine either in the preaching or publiſhing of it as to expect it ſhould doe much good on that ſort of men.</p>
            <p>But to perſons of Piety and Candour, who receive the Word of God into good and honeſt hearts, I hope it may not be unſerviceable. And if it may in any meaſure contribute toward the making us more truly penitent for what is paſt, or a more obedient people for the future, I ſhall think my ſelf happy, and thankfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore him whoſe ſtrength was made manifeſt in my weakneſs.</p>
            <p>To the Divine Protection and Bleſſing I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly commend your Lordſhip, your Honourable Brethren and this great City which flouriſhes under your juſt and prudent Adminiſtration, and intreat your acceptance of this poor Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that I am in all humility,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obedient and faithfull Servant,</hi> William Hopkins.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94731:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Lord Mayor, &amp;c. <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1683.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN, V. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Behold, thou art made whole: Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the beginning of this chapter S. <hi>John</hi> relates a memorable paſſage which is not recorded by any other Hiſtorian either Sacred or Profane. That there was at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a pool called <hi>Betheſda,</hi> whoſe waters were at ſome times endued with a medicinal virtue. <hi>For an Angel went down at a certain ſeaſon into the pool, and troubled the waters: whoſoever then firſt after the troubling of the water ſtepped in, was made whole of whatſoever diſeaſe he had,</hi> v. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94731:4"/>
               <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Light-foot,</hi> Hor. Heb. in <hi>Joan. Tertullian.</hi> adverſus Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, cap. <hi>13.</hi> ſub finem.</note> How long thoſe waters had been endued with that miraculous virtue, or how long it continued after our Saviour's Aſcenſion is unknown. This onely is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from Hiſtory, that Miracles and the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy had ceaſed in the Jewiſh Church for ſeveral a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges before our Saviour's birth, and both were reſtored but a little while before his manifeſtation in the fleſh: And it is probable this miraculous water was one of the ſigns of his coming; it being a fit reſemblance of that more pretious <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>bath,</hi> his own bloud, whoſe healing efficacy was not confined to a ſingle Patient, but redounded to the advantage of the whole world, and whoſe purifying virtue was truly univerſal and able <hi>to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſilence of the other Evangeliſts and the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh writers, as well as <hi>Theophylact</hi>'s hint, may have occaſioned the Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> to ſuſpect, that the virtue of this pool was not miraculous, but natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. And he offers this Philoſophical account of the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond <hi>on</hi> Joh. V. <hi>Annot.</hi> a.</note>That the waters were impregnated with ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial qualities derived from the entrails of beaſts ſlain for Sacrifice, which he conceives were caſt into that pool. And that at ſome ſet times an Officer or Meſſenger (not one of God's Angels) was ſent in, who had skill to diſturb the waters, <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſtir up and diffuſe the particles of the entrails and bloud in which the virtue lay; whereupon for ſome time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, till the virtuous particles ſank again to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, that pool was an healing Bath.</p>
            <p>The Hypotheſis is, I confeſs, very ingenious, and he confirms it with pertinent obſervations of what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in ſome diſtempers the Patient hath received, by the application of the warm skin, or vitals of a beaſt, or by putting him into the belly of a beaſt newly killed and opened.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94731:4"/>But if we well conſider them, ſeveral circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Evangeliſt's Narrative cannot conſiſt with this Hypotheſis. For though the entrails of beaſts may have a ſuppling and reſtorative virtue, and in the way of a fomentation may relieve pains and weakneſs in the limbs, bruiſes and withered members, yet this is ſhort of the efficacy which S. <hi>John</hi> aſcribes to this bath, which ſeems to have been an univerſal Medicine. Now there are many diſtempers for which bathing and fomentation are no proper methods of cure; and if we muſt reſtrain the univerſal particle <hi>whatſoever</hi> to the diſeaſes mentioned by S. <hi>John,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V.</note> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the blind, who are expreſly named, very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to receive benefit thereby.</p>
            <p>Again, If thoſe cures were wrought by the ſtirring up and mixing of the virtue of the entrails with the water, it might almoſt conſtantly have been kept in motion, and many more might have enjoyed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of cure, than it ſhould ſeem there did. For the waters were troubled onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſeldom, at a certain ſeaſon,</hi> ſome think, but once in the year,<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>'s An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</note> at the Paſſover; others, at all the three great Feaſts, and though perhaps ſeveral times at each Feaſt, yet at moſt but once in the day.</p>
            <p>Again, Had the cure been wrought by any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral efficacy, why ſhould the benefit be limited to him alone who firſt ſtepped in after the troubling of the water? it's ſcarce credible that the Pool was no lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than to hold one perſon, if the entrails of all the Paſchal Sacrifices (<note n="†" place="margin">No leſs than <hi>255600</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the computation Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> takes notice of in this Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> whoſe number was very great) were ordinarily caſt into it. If the virtuous particles of the entrails were well diffuſed, why might not theſe waters have cured as many as went in before they ſubſided? If it be ſaid, they ſunk quickly, it's much they ſhould cure ſo much as one patient, for it's
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94731:5"/>
by long continuance in them, and frequent uſe, that baths relieve inveterate weakneſs, whereas it ſhould ſeem once deſcending into the pool was ſufficient.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, This account of the matter is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ſentiments of the Ancients, who aſcribe theſe cures to a ſupernatural power, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note n="‖" place="margin">In <hi>Joannem</hi> Homil. <hi>35.</hi> &amp; Tom. <hi>5.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>62.</hi> in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralyt. demiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum per tec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> more than once comparing the Pool of <hi>Betheſda</hi> to the Baptiſmal waters, makes the former a miraculous type of the latter.</p>
            <p>I need not labour farther in confutation of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which that excellent Authour delivers modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and onely as a conjecture, and therefore ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſhew how our Bleſſed Lord,<note place="margin">Acts X. 38.</note> 
               <hi>who went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout doing good,</hi> came to this healing pool, and, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a multitude of expectants, is pleaſed to ſingle out this poor Paralytick as the meeteſt object for him to ſhew his Divine power and compaſſion upon. Not that he deſerved better than others, many of whoſe diſeaſes might be pure infelicities, whereas his long infirmity was the fruit of his Sins: The miſerable circumſtances under which he lay, were the onely motives of our Saviour's pity.</p>
            <p>He conſidered, 1. the long time he had been in that weak and helpleſs condition, 38 years, and perhaps had for the greateſt part of that time in vain waited at <hi>Betheſda</hi> for cure.<note place="margin">V. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus ſaw him lie, and knew that he had been a long time in that caſe.</hi> And then, 2ly, he conſidered his Impotence and Poverty, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him unlikely ever to receive help there, being unable to ſtep firſt into the pool after the troubling of the waters,<note place="margin">V. 7.</note> and having no friend or ſervant <hi>to put him in.</hi> His ſad condition moved pity in the Bleſſed <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> who immediately, with a word, reſtored ſpirits to his weak nerves, and ſtrength and motion to his wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered limbs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94731:5"/>Such a ſurpriſing mercy might carry a man of no extraordinary devotion to the Temple with a Soul full of Joy and Thankfulneſs. Thither the impotent perſon quickly went, to offer up his Praiſes to God; and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Saviour followed him, to complete the cure which was ſcarce half wrought at <hi>Betheſda.</hi> His Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy indeed was there made whole, but his better part, his Soul, ſtill needed the Phyſician; and till that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were healed, the cauſe of his long infirmity ſtill remained, and he was in danger of relapſing into a much worſe condition than that out of which he was newly recovered. The Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> therefore applies him to the cure of his ſpiritual maladies, and in my Text preſcribes a Sovereign Antidote againſt all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible danger of a relapſe, gives him this <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyril.</hi> Alex. in loc.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this <hi>wholſome ghoſtly advice, Behold, thou art made whole: Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words I ſhall obſerve three Particulars hinted by S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> on this place.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. <hi>in loc.</hi> Joh. IX. 2, 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. An implicit Accuſation and gentle Reproof of his paſt life. A plain intimation that his tedious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily diſtemper was the puniſhment of his Sins. Our Saviour's infinite candour, which abſolved both <hi>the blind man</hi> and <hi>his parents,</hi> and declared, that his cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ought not to be imputed either to his own or their Sins, could not acquit this impotent perſon. <note n="‖" place="margin">Chryſ. <hi>Tom.</hi> V. <hi>Hom.</hi> 62.</note> He doth not openly ſhame him before the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes at <hi>Betheſda,</hi> He doth not publickly reproach his former lewd converſation: but finds him out in the Temple; and privately admoniſhes him to amend his life. <hi>Sin no more,</hi> or as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may be rendred, <hi>Sin no longer now,</hi> implies him formerly to have been a gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sinner, and that his long infirmity was his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94731:6"/>2. Theſe words are an Admonition, and contain wholſome advice for the future conduct of his life. <hi>Sin no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in loc.</note>3. This Admonition is enforced with a twofold ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, the one drawn from the obligation which was laid upon him by this great mercy of his miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous cure, and the other from the danger of a relapſe. He puts him in mind of the ſignal favour he had new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received of God, <hi>Behold, thou art made whole,</hi> [by a miracle,] and oughteſt not, in point of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to offend the Authour of ſo great a bleſſing. And then withall he ſets before him the danger of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his old vomit, threatning him not onely with the forfeiture of the mercy thus miraculouſly conferred upon him, but alſo with ſome heavier Judgment, <hi>leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus opened the words, I ſhall deduce from them theſe three very natural and eaſie Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That great calamities are generally inflicted by God for the puniſhment of Sin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That when God is pleaſed to remove ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, we are obliged to forſake thoſe Sins for which they were inflicted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That if upon the removal of ſuch calamities we do not forſake thoſe Sins for which they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, we may juſtly dread much ſorer Judgments.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak briefly to each of theſe in order, and in concluſion apply all to this Solemn occaſion.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Great calamities are generally inflicted by God for the puniſhment of Sin. I ſay, <hi>generally,</hi> not always; for God hath other ends in ſome afflictions, when
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94731:6"/>
they concern onely the ſingle perſons that ſuffer them. And yet even theſe are for the moſt part pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and ſhould be ſo eſteemed by the Sufferers: but to great Societies, to Nations and Cities, they are always puniſhments. Though God doth not now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe in ſo immediate and extraordinary a way in the government of the Kingdoms of the world, as he did in that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the form of whoſe govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was a Theocracy,<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi> his Peculium Dei. <hi>Joſeph.</hi> contra <hi>Appi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,</hi> &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquit. lib. <hi>4. Moſes</hi> ſic lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui docetur, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the ſupreme civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate was but a Vice roy or Deputy to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who was their King, who gave them their Political Laws and frequently executed them alſo upon Offenders with his own hand; yet doth his Providence ſtill vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly appear in recompencing politick Bodies in this world according to their works; in protecting and proſpering religious, vertuous and juſt Nations, and in puniſhing ſuch as are profane, diſſolute and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. And, in truth, if it pleaſe God to puniſh Cities and Nations, as ſuch, he muſt doe it in this world; for though every member of any Society muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the Judgment ſeat of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and may receive the things done in the body, as well Politick as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, whether they be good or bad; yet thoſe Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties themſelves will ceaſe with this world, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be puniſhed in the next.</p>
            <p>Now there concur two very different cauſes to the puniſhment of Sinners, <hi>viz.</hi> The Righteouſneſs of God, and their own Unrighteouſneſs. The latter juſtly meriting thoſe calamities which the former inflicts. So that in every ſad Providence we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the juſt hand of God lifted up againſt us, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſing the evil works of our own hands upon us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In all our Sufferings we muſt behold the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hand of God, by whoſe Providence afflictions
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94731:7"/>
befall ſinfull men. For, as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith, <hi>Job</hi> V. 6. <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction cometh not forth out of the duſt, nor doth trouble ſpring out of the ground.</hi> The moſt inconſiderable and ſeemingly contingent events,<note place="margin">Matt. XI. 29. Prov. XVI. 33.</note> ſuch as the <hi>fall of a Sparrow,</hi> or the <hi>turn of a die,</hi> are under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Divine Providence. And therefore it muſt needs be much more intereſſed in what befalls ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a creature as Man, nay great Societies of men. The Calamities of Cities and Kingdoms muſt not be imputed to mere chance; nor may we think that God is no farther concerned with them, than by his general concourſe with the immediate and ſecond cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them.</p>
            <p>If we ſuffer by Fire or by Sea, by immoderate Rain or Drought, we muſt behold theſe <hi>as ſcourges in God's hand.</hi> If we are puniſhed either by War or Peſtilence, we muſt eſteem both our Enemies and the deſtroying Angel <hi>God's Miniſters</hi> and the <hi>Executioners</hi> of his <hi>juſt,</hi> though <hi>fierce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>—</note> 
               <hi>wrath. He makes the creatures his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons for vengeance on his enemies,</hi> Wiſd. V. 18.</p>
            <p>If the Sea overflow its banks, and drown a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, it's by God's commiſſion that the Ocean enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges its Territories and ſwallows up a ſinfull Land. If Famine afflict a Nation, whether the immediate cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be exceſſive drought or rains, know, that it is the Lord who breaks the <hi>ſtaff of bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. V. 16.</note> who ſendeth unſeaſonable rain, and withholdeth it in its ſeaſon. If the Peſtilence rage in a City and conſume its Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, this evil alſo is of the Lord. If we undergo the miſeries of War, and our Enemies prevail over us, we muſt remember,<note place="margin">Iſa. XXXIV. 6.</note> that it is the <hi>ſword of the Lord</hi> that is in their hands and <hi>fills it ſelf with our bloud. They ſhall know that I am the LORD when I put MY SWORD into the hand of the King of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> Ezek. XXX. 25. It is the Lord of hoſts that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94731:7"/>
pleads with us by the Sword; and ſells us into the hands of our enemies, becauſe we have ſold our ſelves to work wickedneſs. If the Fire conſume our dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and lay our Cities in Aſhes, the Prophet tells us, that God pleads with ſinfull fleſh <hi>by fire</hi> as well as <hi>by the ſword.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. LXVI. 16. Hoſ. VIII. 14.</note> 
               <hi>He ſendeth fire upon our Cities</hi> and flames to <hi>devour our Palaces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, by whatever hands we ſuffer, by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever inſtruments he pleaſes to afflict us, we muſt <hi>hear the rod</hi> and conſider <hi>who hath appointed it,</hi> Mich. VI. 9. We muſt acknowledge our ſufferings to be from God, and the chaſtiſement of our ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whilſt we behold God as the Authour of our calamities, we muſt aſcribe them to his Juſtice,<note place="margin">A Deo quidem punimur, ſed ipſi facimus, ut puniamur, <hi>Salvian.</hi> de Gub. Dei, l. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> and not forget that the cauſe of our ſufferings is in our ſelves. For God would not inflict them, did not we both need and deſerve them. The wrath of God is never revealed but againſt the ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men. And even when his hand is <hi>heavieſt</hi> upon us,<note place="margin">Ezra IX. 13. Job XI. 6. Pſal. CIII. 10.</note> our puniſhments are much <hi>lighter than our iniquities deſerve.</hi> There had been no ſuch thing as Vengeance belonging to God, but for the Wickedneſs of his Rebellious creatures. Sin and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment are as nearly related as the Cauſe and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and the latter in the very notion of it implies the former: For no ſuffering is properly a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unleſs inflicted for Sin. Hence in the language of the Holy Scriptures <hi>to bear ſin or iniquity</hi> ſignifies <hi>to be puniſhed</hi> or <hi>put to death</hi> for it.<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Exod. xxviij. 43. Levit. XXIV. 15, 16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Chriſt is ſaid to bear the ſins of many, <hi>i. e.</hi> in their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Iſa. LIII. 11, 12.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> When a man is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for his Sins, he is ſaid <hi>to eat the fruit of his ways,</hi> Prov. I. 31. to be <hi>recompenſed according to his deeds and the works of his own hands,</hi> Jer. XXV. 14. and <hi>to poſſeſs his iniquity,</hi> Job XIII. 26. All which forms of ſpeech import our ſins to be the meritorious and impulſive cauſe of our calamities.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94731:8"/>And as we muſt acknowledge the Juſtice of God in our ſufferings, ſo muſt we likewiſe own his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his wiſedom and fatherly care of us. In our preſent lapſed condition, in this ſtate of Sin and Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">Rev. III. 19. Heb. XII. 5.</note> he would not truly <hi>love us</hi> ſhould he not, when he ſees it neceſſary, <hi>rebuke and chaſten us.</hi> Should he not <hi>viſit our tranſgreſſions with the rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. Lxxxix. 32, 33, 34.</note> 
               <hi>and our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with ſtripes,</hi> we might have juſt ground to fear that he had <hi>utterly taken his loving-kindneſs from us,</hi> and was about to <hi>break his Covenant.</hi> It will neither conſiſt with the Honour of his Juſtice and Wiſedom, nor yet with his Love to us, that we ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſin without puniſhment.</p>
            <p>I know ſome men refer all to irreſpective Decrees, or tell us that vindictive Juſtice is natural to God, and that he muſt ſacrifice ſome of his creatures in Hell fire to the honour of that Attribute. Nay, that he hath foredamned the greateſt part of mankind by mere Prerogative, and purely for the exerciſe of his Sovereign Power.</p>
            <p>But this account of God differs infinitely from that he gives us of himſelf in the Holy Scriptures. They repreſent him <hi>mercifull and gracious, long-ſuffering and abundant in goodneſs and truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. xxxiv. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>keeping mercy for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin.</hi> They tell us that,<note place="margin">Pſal. CXLV. 9. Ezek. xxxiij. 11. 2 Pet. III. 9.</note> 
               <hi>He is good to all, and that his tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are over all his works. That he hath no pleaſure in the Death of a ſinner.</hi> That <hi>he is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come unto repentance.</hi> He never goes about to get himſelf glory in the death of a ſinner till he ſees the ſinner <hi>will die,</hi> that he is deſperate and incorrigible, that he hardens his heart to that degree, that neither gentleneſs nor ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity can work upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94731:8"/>He ſeeks no advantages againſt his wretched crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Though to puniſh be his <hi>work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. XXVIII. 21.</note> it is his <hi>ſtrange work.</hi> He never ſets about it but with reluctance, and when we compell him to it, for the vindication of Juſtice and Providence. <hi>He doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men,</hi> Lam. III. 33. We have no reaſon to arraign his Juſtice, or murmur at the ſeverity of his Judgments, ſince we ſuffer but the puniſhment and leſs than the deſert of our Sins.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially if we add this conſideration, That the chaſtiſements we bear are <hi>for our profit;</hi> and though <hi>for the preſent,</hi> while we feel the ſmart of them,<note place="margin">Heb. XII. 11.</note> 
               <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are not joyous, but grievous;</hi> yet, if we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them duly, and with patience wait their iſſue, <hi>they will bring forth</hi> to us the peaceable fruits of <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi> As they were intended by our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo will they in the event work for our good. If his judgments teach us Righteouſneſs, and we learn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience by the things which we have ſuffered,<note place="margin">Iſa. XXVII. 9. Heb. XII. 10.</note> 
               <hi>all their fruit will be to take away our ſin,</hi> and <hi>to make us partakers of his Holineſs.</hi> But whatever the effect of our calamities may prove, whether they operate thus kindly or no, we muſt needs juſtifie God amidſt our ſufferings, and take to our ſelves ſhame, confeſſing with <hi>Azarias, Thou art righteous, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Song of the 3 Children, v. 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>in all the things thou haſt done unto us—according to truth and Judgment didſt thou bring all theſe things upon us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our ſins. We have ſinned, we have committed iniquity, departing from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. That when God is pleaſed to remove ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, we are obliged to forſake thoſe Sins for which they were inflicted. <hi>Behold, thou art made whole: Sin no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94731:9"/>What, Sin no more? This is an hard ſaying, who can hear it? Doth our Saviour oblige us to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities? Doth not <hi>Solomon</hi> aſſure us that there is <hi>not a juſt man upon the Earth, that doeth righteouſneſs, and ſinneth not?</hi> Eccleſ. VII. 20. Doth not the Apoſtle ſay that, <hi>In many things we offend all?</hi> James, III. 2. How ſaith our Saviour then, Sin no more?</p>
            <p>But, after all, our Saviour's ſenſe is obvious: he doth not oblige the impotent man to perfect and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs obedience. He too well underſtood our frame, and was too well acquainted with the ſtrength of Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and the weakneſs of frail fleſh and bloud, to make ſpotleſs innocence neceſſary to his continuance in that ſtate of health to which he was miraculouſly reſtored. But this is the ſum and importance of his advice, that upon his recovery he ſhould break off his ſinfull courſe of life, that he ſhould live no longer in habitual and wilfull diſobedience, that he ſhould abſtain from all crying Sins and ſuch as pull down vengeance on mens heads; eſpecially, that he ſhould beware of thoſe ſins (whatever they were) for which God had afflicted him with eight and thirty years weakneſs. This was our Saviour's meaning, and in this ſenſe our Apoſtle muſt be underſtood, 1 <hi>John,</hi> V. 18. where he ſaith, <hi>he that is born of God ſinneth not,</hi> i. e. not habitually, not deliberately, not preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Decepti aut lubrico aetatis, aut nubilo er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris, aut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ignorantiae, aut poſtremò lapſu fragili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis humanae. <hi>Salvian.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Avarit. l. 1.</note> God doth not uſe to follow men with heavy plagues for light offences. It is not every tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is recompenſed in the Earth. Such ſins as are in a ſort the unavoidable effects of humane frailty and ignorance, and are incident to the beſt of men in this ſtate of imperfection and tentation, do not provoke his ſevere reſentments. No, they are Sins of a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per die, of a more enormous and ſcandalous nature
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94731:9"/>
for which God is wont to viſit. Such as have a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of preſumption and malice, or at leaſt proceed from the groſs neglect, if not from the direct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God and Religion. Such Sins as are highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to our Brethren and pernicious to humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. Theſe are the Sins whoſe puniſhment God will not turn away. And when at any time he hath pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed a people for them, and afterwards remembring mercy laies aſide his rod, he expects that ſuch a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould remove thoſe abominations out of the midſt of them.</p>
            <p>For God proſecutes the ſame deſign both in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere and in the more gentle diſpenſations of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. He labours to reclaim a perverſe and croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generation, and omits no kind of method proper to effect it. When he threatens us, he admoniſhes us of our duty and danger; when he chaſtens us, he calls our Sins to remembrance, he admoniſheth us to amend our ways, and put away the evil of our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: when he removes his rod, and again exerciſes patience and longſuffering towards us, he vouchſafes to make a farther experiment, what effect goodneſs will have upon us, and whether it will (at leaſt after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity) lead us to repentance.</p>
            <p>Though in their proſperity Sinners are too apt to deſpiſe the Riches of God's goodneſs, yet after they have been humbled by his heavy Judgments Mercy will be likely to have a more kind and ſucceſsfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. In War we commonly ſee, that the Sword onely begins the Conqueſt, which is finiſhed and crowned by the Victour's clemency. The ſtubborn enemy who valued not his friendſhip, when ſubdued by his victorious arms, will gladly ſubmit to the Conquerour's Mercy. Nay, even wild beaſts that are fierce and miſchievous, are onely brought under
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94731:10"/>
by chains, blows and hunger, and prepared to be throughly tamed and made ſerviceable by their Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per's kindneſs. So that unleſs we are more ſavage and brutiſh than they, after afflictions we muſt needs yield to the irreſiſtible force of God's goodneſs and loving-kindneſs.</p>
            <p>Though we had no ſenſe of our deep obligations to his <hi>infinite goodneſs</hi> whilſt his <hi>bleſſings</hi> flowed in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual and uninterrupted ſtream from that fountain, yet ſince our pipes have been cut off, and bitter wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have flowed inſtead of ſweet and refreſhing ſtreams, certainly if God pleaſe to remember his old loving-kindneſs,<note place="margin">Pſal. CVII. 10.</note> it will reliſh the ſweeter. After we have been bound <hi>in affliction and iron</hi> for our Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt God, if we be once releaſed, ſurely <hi>the cords of a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. XI. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and the</hi> ſoft <hi>bands of love</hi> will hold us faſter than ever. This good ſucceſs God ſeems to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect when his mercy heals thoſe wounds which he made for our Sins. He ſeems to make tryal whether the good effects which appear to have been wrought on us by our Afflictions are real and durable. For whilſt we are under the laſh, the ſucceſs cannot be ſo well and certainly obſerved. The Dog muſt reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his ſickneſs before he will return to his vomit. Whilſt we feel the ſmart of the rod, we are apt to call thoſe Sins to remembrance for which we think our ſelves to ſuffer; we are apt to take up good Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt them; to make fair Promiſes of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to bind them with moſt ſolemn Vows. But the Rod muſt be removed before we can come to the Teſt; before it can appear how firm and ſteddy our Reſolutions, how ſincere our Promiſes were, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will faithfully pay unto the Lord thoſe Vows which we made in the day of Trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94731:10"/>So that when it pleaſes God to deliver us out of thoſe miſeries which our Sins have brought upon us, we are to conſider, that we are in <hi>a ſtate of Probation,</hi> we are <hi>upon Tryal.</hi> And we are farther under a double obligation to forſake thoſe Sins for which we lately ſmarted. We have the voluntary obligation of our own Vows upon us, and we are bound in point of Gratitude to God to <hi>Sin no more.</hi> He will eſteem the faithfull <hi>performance</hi> of our <hi>Holy Reſolutions</hi> the moſt <hi>Authentick Evidence</hi> of our <hi>Thankfulneſs,</hi> and our future <hi>Obedience</hi> our beſt <hi>Peace-offering.</hi> When God hath put an end to <hi>his controverſie with a land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. Lxxxv. 8.</note> and vouchſafes yet once more to <hi>ſpeak peace to his people,</hi> he expects that they <hi>ſhould not turn again unto folly.</hi> But in caſe they do not anſwer ſo reaſonable an expectation, if they offer him freſh affronts, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat their old ones, they will find the Truce broken by their own Treachery, and Vengeance returning armed with double fury. Men have no reaſon to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe themſelves Peace ſo long as they boldly put Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to defiance, and fight againſt God. He may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps give them a little reſpite, he may change their puniſhment, and not continually laſh them with the ſame Rod, but till they ceaſe provoking him there will be no end of their calamities.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That if upon the removal of ſuch Calamities we do not forſake thoſe Sins for which they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, we may juſtly dread forer Judgments. <hi>Leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almighty God in dealing with his ſinfull creatures is pleaſed to obſerve the method of skilfull Phyſicians, who begin with the moſt gentle and eaſie remedies, ſearching and cleanſing the wound with as little pain as may be to the Patient; but if the wound putrifie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94731:11"/>
and gangrene, they are forced to proceed to more painfull operations, ſuch as launcing, inciſion and ſearing; and when after all they find the malignity and venome of the gangrene is ſuch as no remedies can conquer, they are forced to cut off the incurable member. Thus doth God at firſt exerciſe the Sinner with gentle corrections, ſeeming to be not without hope that they may prove ſtrong enough to work his Reformation, but if they fail of ſucceſs, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to greater ſeverities in proportion to the guilt and obſtinacy of the Offender. Thus he dealt with his ancient people the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. IX. 1.</note> 
               <hi>At firſt he lightly afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the land of Zabulon and the land of Napthali, and afterwards did more grievouſly afflict her by the way of the Sea.</hi> As men do not mount <hi>per ſaltum</hi> at one leap to the height of all Impiety and Profaneneſs, but wax worſe and worſe by degrees, till at laſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come deſperately wicked: So neither doth God uſe extremity at firſt, he doth not pour out the full vials of his Indignation at once, but his Judgments grow gradually heavier, till at length vengeance accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſheth the ruine of the incorrigible and deſperate Rebel.</p>
            <p>A remarkable inſtance of what hath been ſaid we have in <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who oppreſſed <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and refuſed to obey the voice of the Lord, who by his Prophets commanded them to let his people go. He began with light afflictions, and as oft as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſeemed to repent he removed them: When <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaw there was reſpite, he hardned his heart; whereupon God ſent other Plagues upon <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and followed them with one Judgment after another, puniſhing them firſt in their Waters, then in their Corn and Cattle, next in their Bodies with ſore Blains and Boils; after that, in the Death of their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94731:11"/>
Firſt-born; and laſtly, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> having many times wilfully hardened his own heart, God hardened it pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to his ruine; ſo that purſuing the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> through the Red-ſea he was drowned with his whole Hoſt.</p>
            <p>Nor was this a ſingular caſe, a particular method wherein God dealt onely with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</hi> For thus he treated his own peculiar people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for whoſe ſake he had ſent all thoſe prodigious Plagues on <hi>Egypt.</hi> When they murmured in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, he chaſtiſed them ſeveral ways. When they waxed wanton in the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> and revolted to Idolatry, he ſuffered the neighbour Nations to infeſt their Land, to take their Cities, to defeat their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to oppreſs them and bring them under Tribute: after a while he would deliver them; when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted again, he puniſh'd them ſome other way. As their obſtinacy encreaſed, ſo did his ſeverity. He ſuffered the X Tribes firſt to go into Captivity, and after a while he cauſed the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> to carry away <hi>Juda</hi> Captive, and lay waſte both the City and Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> For 70 years they ſate in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and then God brought back their Captivity, and ſo favoured them that they rebuilt the City and Temple; but as they returned to their ancient dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſo did they to their Sins, and continued a ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked and rebellious generation, deſpiſing the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, contemning his threatnings, killing his Prophets, crucifying his own Son; and having now filled up the meaſure of their iniquities, God delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them into the hands of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Nation, burnt the City and Temple of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> raſed their foundations, and litterally fulfilled our Saviour's Prediction,<note place="margin">Matt. XXIV. 2.</note> 
               <hi>that there ſhould not be one ſtone left upon another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94731:12"/>Now there are ſeveral ways in which God is wont to bring worſe things upon obſtinate and unreformed Sinners. I ſhall inſtance in Three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When he brings the ſame Calamities thicker and oftner upon them, and though he ſcourge them with the ſame Rod, yet he increaſes the number of their ſtripes. Their enemies make frequent incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon them, they ſuffer by frequent Plagues and Fires.<note place="margin">Pſal. XXXII. 10.</note> Thus, as the Pſalmiſt threatens, <hi>many ſorrows ſhall be to the wicked.</hi> God will raiſe them up ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies on every ſide, and as he threatens the <hi>Jews, he will ſend many fiſhers, and they ſhall fiſh them, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he will ſend many hunters, and they ſhall hunt them,</hi> and make a prey of them, and <hi>he will recompenſe their iniquity and their ſin double.</hi> Jer. XVI. 16, 18. God will double his blow upon every freſh provocation; and as the Sinner multiplies his Tranſgreſſions, ſo will the Divine vengeance multiply his Plagues. <hi>If ye will walk contrary to me,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and will not hearken unto me, I will bring ſeven times more Plagues upon you, according to your ſins.</hi> Lev. XXVI. 21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A worſe thing happens to a relapſed Sinner when God inflicts ſorer and heavier Judgments than before.<note place="margin">1 Kings XII. 14.</note> And this is not unuſual. Thoſe whom <hi>whips</hi> will not reform <hi>he chaſtiſes with Scorpions.</hi> If the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary inſtrument of Diſcipline, <hi>the Rod,</hi> hath been long uſed in vain, <hi>he whets his glittering Sword,</hi> and <hi>bends his Bow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. L. 25.</note> 
               <hi>He opens his Armory,</hi> and ranſacks all the Treaſures of his Wrath for Inſtruments of Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Death, <hi>and brings forth the weapons of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, which is worſe than the ſevereſt Temporal ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity that can befall men, he gives them up to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſenſe,<note place="margin">Jer. v. 23.</note> becauſe <hi>they have</hi> (as the Prophet ſpeaks) <hi>a revolting and rebellious heart.</hi> He caſts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94731:12"/>
them off, as unworthy to be under his farther care and diſcipline; he abandons them to their own luſts, reſolving <hi>to ſtrike them no more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 1.5.</note> that he will <hi>cauſe his fury towards them to reſt,</hi> and that <hi>his Jealouſie ſhall depart from them,</hi> that he <hi>will be quiet, and be angry no more,</hi> Ezek. XVI. 42.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A worſe thing happens to revolting Sinners when God inflicts puniſhments for a worſe purpoſe, not for the Sinner's reformation, but for his own ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. When the ſufferings that befall them are vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictive, and not deſigned for their correction. When Judgments are not intended to teach them righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but to make them examples for the terrour and warning of others. When God ſmites, but not in kindneſs, and there drops no balm from his Rod, but he <hi>wounds them with the wounds of an enemy, and with the chaſtiſement of a cruel one, for the multitude of their iniquities, and becauſe their ſins were increaſed</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">The <hi>Syriack</hi> adds, <hi>even to impenitence.</hi>
               </note>, Jer. XXX. 14. And when neither frequent and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere puniſhments, nor yet intervals of mercy produce fruits meet for repentance, there is all the reaſon in the world for Sinners to expect in ſome or other of the forementioned ways they ſhall feel ſadder effects of God's diſpleaſure. It's both <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>juſt</hi> that ſome worſe thing ſhould come unto them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It's <hi>Neceſſary.</hi> Obſtinate and revolting Sinners <hi>need</hi> ſharper afflictions and heavier judgments to rouze and work upon them. For by frequent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes into Sin, and perſeverance in it, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract an ill habit of Soul; their diſtempers get ſtrength; and the more inveterate they are, the greater difficulty there will be in removing them. For this reaſon relapſed Sinners will need to repeat their bitter potions the oftner, and the doſe muſt be increaſed in proportion to the malignity of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94731:13"/>
eaſe, if gentle medicines have no effect, the bills muſt be altered, ſtrong Phyſick muſt be adminiſtred, and the ill humours evacuated by more violent and churliſh Purgatives. When men grow worſe and worſe under the milder diſpenſations of Providence, and preſume to <hi>add ſin to ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. XXX. 1. Pſal. LXIX. 27.</note> there is no help for them, but God muſt alſo, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, <hi>add iniquity to their iniquity,</hi> i. e. increaſe the ſeverity of their puniſhments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it is Neceſſary, ſo alſo is it <hi>Juſt.</hi> It is a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous thing with God, in regard ſuch obſtinate and backſliding Sinners <hi>deſerve</hi> ſorer judgments. Repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sin contracts a deeper guilt, and all mitigating pleas are inſignificant, when crimes become habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, eſpecially under the circumſtances of the perſon in my Text. When men ſin on after great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and great Deliverances, it is an argument of great Preſumption and Malice; that men are wilfull and ſtubborn, and, as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Job</hi> XXXIV. 37. <hi>Add rebellion to their ſin.</hi> Their guilt is alſo farther aggravated by their Ingratitude, which is a Sin of the fouleſt complexion and deepeſt ſtain. No Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is more unpardonable than the abuſe of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. It is recorded by the Pſalmiſt as an aggravation of the ſtupid perverſeneſs of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> That <hi>they underſtood not God's wonders in Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. CVII. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not the multitude of his mercies; but provoked him at the Sea, even at the RED SEA.</hi> Every part of the verſe is a ſmart reproach of their ſottiſh Unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. That they took no warning by God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Judgments on the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat his Mercies towards themſelves no leſs wonderfull; not ſingle mercies, but great multitudes of them; and, after all, <hi>provoked him at the Sea, even at the RED SEA.</hi> The repetition is an emphatical aggravation of their Ingratitude, <hi>Even at the red Sea,</hi> through
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94731:13"/>
which God had juſt before miraculouſly opened them a ſafe and dry paſſage, where he had deſtroyed their enemies before their eyes, and ſecured them from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver returning to their former bondage; there they murmured againſt him and provoked him. When the <hi>hand of the Lord hath been lifted up againſt</hi> the wicked <hi>but they will not ſee it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. XXVI. 10, 11.</note> and afterwards favour hath been ſhewn them, <hi>but they will not learn righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> it is an argument that <hi>they offend of malicious Wickedneſs,</hi> and are not onely unworthy but uncap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of mercy. That they are incorrigible and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, Veſſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction, that farther long-ſuffering will be a ſort of Cruelty to them, and ſwift deſtruction a degree of mercy; nay the onely mercy they are capable of: For it may be ſome little abatement of their miſeries in the next world, that they lived no longer in this, and were not permitted to treaſure up ſo immenſe a weight of wrath as in a long life they would have heaped up unto themſelves.</p>
            <p>In Concluſion, when neither Judgments nor Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies will work reformation, and men preſume to <hi>Sin on</hi> againſt all ſorts of admonitions and obligations to <hi>Sin no more,</hi> what can ſuch wretched creatures expect, but worſe and worſe calamities, even the very worſt of all Plagues: That Vengeance ſhould come arm'd with flames of fire unquenchable and triumph in their Eternal Ruine.</p>
            <p>Thus I have briefly conſidered the three obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I made from the words, and am to crave but a little more of your Patience, whilſt I apply what hath been ſaid to this Solemn occaſion.</p>
            <p>The words of our Saviour in my Text, are a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject very proper for the entertainment of our moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94731:14"/>
thoughts this day:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in loc.</note> and though they were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the impotent man alone, yet were intended for the admonition of us all, who are in circumſtances exactly parallel with his. God had wounded us for our Tranſgreſſions, and hath healed us by a miracle of his mercy. And as Chriſt found him in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo are we all here before the Lord in his houſe of Prayer: and conſidering the happy change of the State of this eminent City, ſince the appointment of this Anniverſary Faſt, I may ſay we are in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon a much like occaſion.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be the name of the Lord, we are not now aſſembled to weep over her ſmoaking Ruines, and to mingle our tears with her aſhes. We have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to bewail her as a diſconſolate Widow, for ſhe ſits as a Queen again,<note place="margin">Pſa. CXLVII. 13.</note> and <hi>her Children within her are bleſſed.</hi> She lies no longer on ruinous heaps, the Scorn and Deriſion of her Enemies, but ſhe is riſen as a Phoenix out of her Aſhes, the aſtoniſhing joy of her friends, and the envy of all that hate her. As that dreadfull Fire which conſumed her, hath been thought a lively reſemblance of the general Conflagration at the laſt day, ſo methinks this City riſen out of the duſt, is no faint Embleme of the Reſurrection. <hi>It is raiſed in glory.</hi> It is rebuilt with greater beauty, its ſtructures both private and publick, Civil and Sacred, are far more magnificent than before. So that I may very well apply the firſt part of our Saviour's words to this great and eminent City. <hi>Behold, thou art made whole:</hi> and add St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s gloſs, <hi>not by thy merit, but by the Divine mercy and power.</hi> For the rebuilding of it in ſo ſhort a time and ſo great Splendour, is little ſhort of a miracle.</p>
            <p>But though we do upon this account, in ſome meaſure forget our Sorrows, yet there is ſtill juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94731:14"/>
for our ſolemn Humiliation this day; to ſpend it in mourning, and in all ſorts of Penitential exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. For though the calamitous effects of the Fire be well nigh worn off, yet whilſt our Sins which kindled it remain, they will afford us perpetual cauſe of Faſting, and give us occaſion to look back with Sorrow, and to look forward with Fear. When we reflect and ſee what deſtruction they have already wrought in this Land and City, who among us hath ſo hard a heart as not to melt into Tears? And when we forecaſt what farther and greater Calamities we have reaſon to apprehend from them, is not the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proſpect enough to make our hearts tremble and melt within us like wax? What is onely intimated in the caſe of the Paralytick is a notorious truth in ours, <hi>Our Sins were the cauſe of the Fire.</hi> We confeſs it in the Publick Office of the Day, we have erected a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Infamy in the midſt of our City, to be an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting memorial of the dreadfull Judgments of God, and the dreadfull Sins of this Generation, and which is ſad to conſider, our Sins themſelves reign in the midſt of us, and teſtify againſt us. I hope therefore no man will have either the Folly or the Impudence to waſh his hands and ſay, <hi>I have contributed no Fuell to theſe Flames of London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though a late Inſcription charge the Papiſts with the Fire, it was not deſigned to abſolve our Sins, the undoubted Boutefeus, and the worſt ſort of Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries. Though it might be intended to continue an immortal hatred of Popery; ſure it was never meant to reconcile us to our provoking abominations. This would have been to ridicule the Wiſedom and Piety of our Governours, and contradict the beſt deſign of the Monument.</p>
            <p>There is nothing ſo much hinders the good effects
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94731:15"/>
of Chaſtiſements, as transferring the blame on others, or imputing them to accidents, and reſting in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes of them. But certainly we have the leaſt Temptation that may be to any thing of that kind: For never were there more viſible tokens of the juſt Vengeance of God, than in the Fire of <hi>London.</hi> Thoſe circumſtances which we are too prone to call acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, that concurred to the ſpreading of the Fire, ſhew the Providence of that God whom we had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked. Whatever creatures aſſiſted to the ſwift propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Flames; whether evil Inſtruments, or the heat and drought of the preceding Summer, or the Winds, they were all God's <hi>Militia</hi> armed againſt us. And neither ſtrong Eaſt-winds nor the famous <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>French</hi> Fire-balls carried on the Fire ſo much as the Trains our Sins had laid in all quarters of the City, and the fierce Blaſts of God's juſt diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>Having ſo ſeverely ſmarted for our Faults already, methinks we ſhould be well diſpoſed to receive our Saviour's advice, <hi>Sin no more.</hi> One would think our ſad experience ſhould afford us ſome ſecurity againſt ſuffering again in the ſame way, and on the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. We ſee that Beaſts and Birds will not be twice taken in the ſame ſnare; and ſhall we be more irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal than Brutes, and ſuffer our ſelves to be often o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken with the ſame Faults? Oh that we could be bleſt with ſo happy a ſight as that Reformation one might reaſonably expect,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer. VI. 28.</hi> Iis ipſis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus coerceban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur plagis ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lera creſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant; ut puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, poenam ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam criminum quaſi matrem eſſe vitiorum, <hi>Salv.</hi> de Gub. l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> that either ſo heavy a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the Fire, or ſo great a Mercy as the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of this City, ſhould ſingly produce! But alas, <hi>we are all grievous Revolters.</hi> We have been made worſe by our Afflictions and hardned by our Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, we like the Anvil have reverberated the ſtrokes of God's hammer, and they have made no impreſſion upon us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94731:15"/>It is a ſad Obſervation that <hi>Lactantius</hi> makes of the <hi>Heathen Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactant.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> niſi dum in malis ſunt.</note> 
               <hi>That they never remember God but in times of publick Calamity.</hi> And yet <hi>Salvian</hi>'s obſervation of the incorrigible temper of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Romans</hi> is much more lamentable;<note place="margin">Neque ullam penitus Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni orbis aut Romani nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis portionem, quamlibèt graviter pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis coeleſtibus caeſam un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam fuiſſe correctam. <hi>Salvian.</hi> de Gub. l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That no part of the Roman Empire, though chaſtiſed with the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt plagues by Heaven, was reformed thereby.</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us to conſider how far both theſe ſad obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be verified of us, and whether what the Prophet ſaith of <hi>Judah</hi> may not be too truly and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently applied to us. <hi>This is a Nation that obeyeth not the voice of the Lord, neither receiveth Correction,</hi> Jer. VII. 28. How little influence had this ſore Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon us? Did thoſe of us that eſcaped that Plague repent of their Sins?<note place="margin">Zach. XI. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Did the Fir-tree howle becauſe the Cedar was fallen, or the Oaks of Baſhan for the Foreſt of the Vintage?</hi> Did our leſſer Cities and neighbouring Places take warning by this Calamity of our Metropolis? No ſure, for then they would not, as ſince they have done, have taſted of the ſame cup. How did the Sufferers behave themſelves? was there any viſible amendment? did they come purer out of the Fire? Nothing leſs. The Fire that conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med our eſtates, abated nothing of our Luxury; and the Flames of our Luſt raged, when moſt of the fuell that had maintained them was ſpent. How many here, as <hi>Salvian</hi> obſerves at <hi>Triers,</hi> lay drunk up and down in the warm ruines? How did we ruffle it in rich Silks, Lace and all ſorts of bravery, when it would have better become us to have lain proſtrate before God in Sackcloth and Aſhes? How many were feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and carouſing at the Tavern, when they ſhould have been in the Temple faſting and deprecating far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſeries? When the greateſt part of the City lay in heaps, and the poor remainders of it were black
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94731:16"/>
and disfigured by the Fire, when which way ſoever we turned our eyes, we could not avoid obſerving our deſolations, and the ſad marks of God's diſpleaſure, how few of us abated the leaſt delight, ſaw one Play the leſs, or ſpent in Devotion one hour the more? If any did not run to the ſame exceſs of riot they had done before,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Salv.</hi> de Gub. l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> was it not, as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Miſerioe beneficium, non diſciplinoe,</hi> rather to be aſcribed to their Poverty than their Vertue?</p>
            <p>But perhaps theſe ſevere courſes ſuited not our temper, it may be we are of that generous diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is to be wrought on by kindneſs, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours have not been ill beſtowed upon us. I would to God it were ſo.</p>
            <p>But alas, is not the contrary evident? Doth not Proſperity make us proud and wanton?<note place="margin">Deut. xxxii. 15.</note> Have <hi>we not with Jeſurun waxed fat and kicked, have we not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the God that made us, and lightly eſteemed the Rock of our Salvation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quievit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumper Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacia, nec ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men noſtrorum malitia. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſerant ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes à civibus nec cives à ſuis ſceleribus, <hi>Gildas</hi> de Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid. Britan. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Philo</hi> in vita <hi>Moſis.</hi>
               </note> How have we in the midſt of God's bleſſings forgotten all Sobriety and Gratitude, forgotten both God and our ſelves? The lucid Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of mercy have not brought us into our right minds, nor yet prevailed with us for the leaſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinning. As <hi>Gildas</hi> complains of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours. Nay, as it is obſerved of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the onely uſe we have made of that reſpite we have had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Judgments, hath been like Wreſtlers, to take breath, to recover ſpirits and ſtrength for a freſh combat with Heaven, and that we may be able with greater fury and violence to ſly in the face of God.</p>
            <p>Had we been (as is ſuggeſted) of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous temper that muſt be managed by fair means, God hath made ſufficient Tryal of us in that way.</p>
            <p>He hath heaped favours upon us, and even laden
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94731:16"/>
us with his benefits.<note place="margin">Iſai. XLIII. 24.</note> But in return we have <hi>made him to ſerve with our ſins, and wearied him with our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</hi> If the Fire drave out the unclean Spirit that haunted our old buildings, he ſeems to be now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with ſeven other evil Spirits more wicked than himſelf, and to have taken poſſeſſion of our new habitations. For our Impiety and Contempt of God is greater than ever, our Pride and Vanity prodigious, our Luxury and Debauchery hath outſtript all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of former ages, and are not to be out-done,<note place="margin">Nil erit ulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius quod noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris moribus addat Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas— <hi>Juv.</hi> Sat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> I wiſh they never may be matched by the generations to come. Have not Oppreſſion, Deceit and Perjury o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſpread us? And may not that be ſaid of <hi>London</hi> that the Prophet ſpake of <hi>Gilead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. VI. 18.</note> 
               <hi>It is a City of them that work iniquity, and is polluted with bloud?</hi> Are not Adultery and Whoredom eſteemed ſo venial Sins, that they are ſeldom chaſtiſed with greater ſeverity than a ſmile? Is not the cry of Sins gone up to Heaven, like the cry of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and yet we dread not a like over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw?</p>
            <p>Nay, as though our Wickedneſs brought on ruine too ſlowly whilſt it operated onely in a moral way, as the meritorious cauſe of it, we have of late traded in thoſe Sins which have a natural and more quick tendency to Deſtruction. We have rent the Church by cauſleſs Schiſms, and divided the Kingdom againſt it ſelf by diſloyal Factions. We have been Heady and Ungovernable, which is the moſt certain ſign of approaching ruine. In the heat of our clamorous zeal for the Proteſtant Religion we have diſhonoured it in the higheſt degree: and after all our fierce outcries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery, the worſt of its abominations have been committed amongſt us. God ſpeaks thus to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah. Thou that haſt judged thy Siſters</hi> [Samaria and Sodom] <hi>bear thine own ſhame for thy ſins which thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94731:17"/>
haſt committed more abominable than they: they are more righteous than thou: be confounded and bear thy ſhame,</hi> in that <hi>thou haſt juſtified thy ſiſters,</hi> Ezek. XVI. 52. Is not this diſcourſe very applicable to us? May not God thus reproach us, <q>You have judged your Siſter <hi>Rome,</hi> but have equalled if not outdone her abominations. And the villanies you condemn <hi>in her</hi> you have juſtified by worſe practices?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Are there <hi>Jeſuits</hi> among the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſo are there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, if agreement with them in their worſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and practices may intitle men to the Name who want almoſt nothing elſe but the Order and Habit? Are their <hi>Jeſuits</hi> dangerous Incendiaries? ſo are ours. Do the <hi>Romiſh Jeſuits</hi> ſubject Princes to the Pope? ours ſubject them to the People. Do their <hi>Jeſuits</hi> contrive the depoſing and murthering of Kings? ſo do ours. Do they give the Pope a power to abſolve Subjects from their Allegiance, and diſpenſe with their Oaths? ours make quicker work of it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that piece of Superſtition and Formality allow e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man to doe it for himſelf. Do they allow Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation and mental Reſervation? ours doe worſe, who condemn it in the Principle, but admit it in Practice. Do they make Oaths and Sacraments the Bonds of iniquity, the Seals of ſecrecy in their helliſh deſigns? ours are not very unlike them, who conceal as helliſh Treaſons, contrary to their Oaths to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them; who take Oaths and Sacraments to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie them for the ſervice of a Faction, and to poſſeſs themſelves of Power to ruine both Church and State. Do they at <hi>Rome</hi> propagate Religion by Aſſaſſination and Maſſacres? there have been alſo thoſe among us who ſtuck at neither for the accompliſhment of their Deviliſh Plots. And though they do not canonize or ſaint Traitours as the Pope doth, they dub them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94731:17"/>
               <hi>HEROES,</hi> and <hi>ASSERTORS</hi> of <hi>RELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON</hi> and <hi>LIBERTY;</hi> which poor reward may for ought I know animate our Zealots to as deſperate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, as a Saintſhip doth the <hi>Romiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I conſider what zeal for the Purity of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion theſe men pretend, that they are for purer Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations not onely than the <hi>Roman,</hi> but even the beſt reformed Churches; that they would be thought <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatiſſimi,</hi> the moſt ſincere, moſt zealous, nay the onely Proteſtants in the Nation, theſe pretences ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate their crimes beyond thoſe of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Traytors. And I ſhall not fear to ſay, <hi>they have juſtified their Siſter, and the Papiſts are more righteous than they.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, our bloud Feuds, and the deviliſh Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracies of Atheiſts and Enthuſiaſts preſage ruine to us: and we act as though we deſigned to prevent the ſtroke of divine Vengeance, and become our own Executioners.</p>
            <p>When the greateſt part of this City lay in aſhes, and its wealth was conſumed by the Fire, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but deſolation preſented it ſelf to our view, and thouſands lay in the Fields, a man would have thought <hi>London</hi> was as miſerable as it could be made. But when I behold the univerſal Corruption of manners, the Debauchery, the Uncleanneſs, Profaneneſs and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abominations which are committed in it, without ſhame, and though not with allowance, yet with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity; when I ſee how factious,<note place="margin">Non tam mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, domorúm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que exuſtione Civitas perire dicenda eſt, quàm juſtitiae exterminio, &amp; morum corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione. <hi>Nic.</hi> de Clemangiis Ep. <hi>101.</hi>
               </note> heady and ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable men are, I muſt needs profeſs, that in all its preſent Splendour I look upon the condition of this City to be worſe than when it lay in ruines. For a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not ſo effectually undone, by the demoliſhing of its Walls, and burning of its Houſes, as by the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing Religion, Righteouſneſs, Truth and Peace out of the midſt of it, and the general corruption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94731:18"/>
And 'tis a far leſs lamentable ſight to behold a people under ſuch calamities, than to ſee them unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed nay worſe after them.</p>
            <p>This ſeems to be our caſe. We have paſſed through the Fire, but are not purified, our droſs remains in us. We are ſtupid and inſenſible, and it was but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to erect a Pillar in remembrance of it, for the Sufferers themſelves ſeem to have forgotten it. For this ſolemn Anniverſary Humiliation is dwindled into almoſt nothing, ſaving (I am loth to ſay the Pomp, I hope 'tis the Devotion of) <hi>this Great Appearance.</hi> How do many flie the Penance of this Faſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain themſelves with all ſorts of Pleaſures at their Country-Houſes?<note place="margin">Iſai. XXII. 12.13.</note> On this <hi>day when the Lord of Hoaſts calls us to weeping and mourning,</hi> there is nothing but <hi>joy and mirth eating Fleſh and drinking Wine.</hi> I ſhould not have mentioned this to this Honourable Auditory, but that I have my ſelf with ſome trouble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern obſerved it to be the Practice of many grave and eminent Citizens. They ſeem to have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that dreadfull Fire, and no fear of thoſe worſe Judgments we have to apprehend. In one ſenſe they will never forget the Fire, they will tell you they feel it yet in their Eſtates, they will with the impotent man as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tell tragical Stories of their loſſes,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. <hi>Tom.</hi> 5. <hi>hom.</hi> 62.</note> how many hundreds and thouſands they are the worſe for it, and perhaps magnify their loſſes beyond truth; but they forget why God brought this great calamity upon the City, and how much fuell their own Sins contributed to its flames.</p>
            <p>If ever our Saviour's advice was neceſſary, ſure 'tis ſo now, and I can never too often repeat and preſs it. <hi>O ſin no more, ſin no more.</hi> The meaſure of our iniquities ſeems to be well nigh filled up, and unleſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94731:18"/>
a ſpeedy and general Reformation appeaſe the wrath of God, it will be too great a favour for us to expect that he ſhould ſmite us any more for our Correction, we muſt look for ſome worſe thing than either Plague or Fire or any other of thoſe Judgments that have hitherto come upon us.</p>
            <p>Leſt <hi>a worſe thing happen unto us?</hi> How is it poſſible? No Fire can ever ſpread in theſe new brick buildings, as the former did in the old timber-houſes. Some worſe thing? What can be worſe than ſuch a general Calamity, which ruin'd thouſands, which not onely impoveriſht the City, but the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, what have we worſe to fear?</p>
            <p>My Brethren, be not deceived: Though ye have drunk of a bitter cup,<note place="margin">Rev. XIV. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> And<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Caeſar. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> yet its bitterneſs hath been hitherto taken off with a large mixture of mercy: ye have not yet taſted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Wine of his wrath unmixt, ye have not drunk up the dregs thereof. Flatter not your ſelves with the thoughts that the worſt is already paſt.<note place="margin">Pſal. XC. 11.</note> Ye do not underſtand <hi>the power of his Anger,</hi> and therefore do not entertain juſt fears of his diſpleaſure. He can if he ſee good puniſh you again in the ſame way, and with as much eaſe lay waſte your Stately New-Buildings, as he did the old Rotten ones. Though your City be raiſed in <hi>glory</hi> 'tis not raiſed <hi>in incorruption.</hi> If it be not in ſo great danger of caſual Fire, yet ſure the Vengeance of God can propagate ſuch a Calamity farther than all the Malice, Art and Induſtry of the worſt Boutefeus. Where the breath of the Lord kindles a Fire, all things are as Hay and Stubble before it.</p>
            <p>Have ye nothing worſe to fear? recollect your ſelves, and conſider what ye at that time feared, but through the mercy of God eſcap'd a Maſſacre by the bloudy hands of thoſe, who burnt your City. Your fire
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94731:19"/>
might have been like that <hi>Rev.</hi> VIII. 7. <hi>Mingled with bloud.</hi> God might have made your ruines everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Deſolations; and whereas he hath graciouſly ſaid unto this <hi>City thou ſhalt be built,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. XLIV. 28.</note> and to our <hi>Temples your Foundations ſhall be laid.</hi> The Lord might have devoted <hi>London</hi> as he did <hi>Jericho,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. VI. 26.</note> and have laid a Curſe upon the man, who ſhould have preſumed to lay the firſt Stone of its New-Buildings.</p>
            <p>Have ye nothing worſe to fear? hath not God by a miracle of mercy newly diſcovered and delivered us from a greater danger? There wanted onely the <hi>PERMISSION</hi> of <hi>HEAVEN</hi> to have brought <hi>a worſe thing</hi> upon us. For <hi>HELL</hi> was ready to <hi>BREAK LOOSE</hi> again upon us with more <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous fury</hi> than ever,<note place="margin">See his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note> In the Murther of our <hi>KING</hi> and his Royal Brother, in the Aſſaſſination of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſters of State, and the Principal Magiſtrates of this City, and all the miſcheivous conſequences of Cruelty, and Confuſion. Had not God by his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Providence prevented them, the Combuſtions of Eighty three, might have proved more fatal to the City and Nation than the Flames of Sixty ſix.</p>
            <p>Methinks I hear the Voice of God our Saviour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this great deliverance ſaying to us of this Nation and City, as he did to the Impotent man in my Text, <hi>Sin no more.</hi> And if we can be but ſo wiſe and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as to receive his Admonition, we are ſecure from the Threatning that follows it, <hi>Leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me then <hi>beſeech you,</hi> Brethren, in Chriſt's ſtead, <hi>both by the Judgments and mercies</hi> of the Lord,<note place="margin">Rom. XII. 1. 2 Cor. V. 20.</note> 
               <hi>be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God.</hi> As ye deſire the continuance of his bleſſings, or as ye would avert worſe Calamities than any ye have yet felt. As ye tender the peace and Proſperity of this City.<note place="margin">1. Cor. XV. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Awake to Righteouſneſs, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94731:19"/>
ſin no more: Waſh you, make you clean;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. I. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>put away the evil of your doings before the eyes of the Lord, ceaſe to doe evil, learn to doe well.</hi> Have compaſſion on your ſelves, forſake <hi>thoſe iniquities which ſeparate between you and your God, and have hid his face from you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. LIX. 2.</note> if you hope to prevail with him to be mercifull to you and bleſs you. Improve this opportunity of making your peace with him, which the Wiſedom and Piety of our Government hath put into your hands. Let the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the late dreadfull Fire teach you the Fear of the Lord, which is the trueſt Wiſedom, and the beſt Preſervative from the like Calamities. Let the ſincerity of this days Humiliation appear in its happy influence on the future conduct of your lives. Let it ſo refreſh the memory of God's Judgments and your ſins, as to make you walk humbly with him the whole year after. The good effects of a Faſt depend not ſo much upon the ſolemnity as the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of our Repentance: not ſo much upon the number of our Prayers or the noiſe of our cries, as on the lifting up of holy hands and clean hearts to God. In vain do we lift up our voice,<note place="margin">Fruſtrà ete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim vox ad Deum clamat cum ſcelerata vita recla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. <hi>Nic.</hi> de Clemang. Ep. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> and cry mightily to the Lord for mercy, whilſt our Sins cry out againſt us, and call louder to heaven for Vengeance. Without reformation we may proclaim, but cannot ſanctify a Faſt; the calling of a ſolemn aſſembly this day will be but an affront to God: Our Sacrifice will be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among our abominations, and our Prayers will be turned into Sin.</p>
            <p>If we deſire to appeaſe the wrath of God, which ſeems not to be yet turned away, we muſt ſanctifie ſuch a Faſt as he hath choſen.<note place="margin">Dan. IV. 27.</note> We muſt <hi>break off our Sins by Righteouſneſs, and our Iniquities by ſhewing Mercy on the poor;</hi> eſpecially ſuch as have been Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers by this and the like Calamities. We muſt <hi>looſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94731:20"/>
the bands of wickedneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. LVIII. 6, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and let the oppreſſed go free;</hi> we muſt <hi>deal our bread to the hungry, and bring the poor out-caſts into our houſes; when we ſee the naked, we muſt cover them, and not hide our ſelves from our own fleſh.</hi> We muſt <hi>draw out our ſoul to the hungry, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the afflicted. Then ſhall we CALL upon the LORD, and he will ANSWER; we ſhall CRY, and he will ſay, HERE I AM. Our</hi> few <hi>old waſte places ſhall be built, and our</hi> imperfect <hi>foundations ſhall be raiſed up, and the Lord ſhall for ever be the RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PAIRER OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R BREACHES.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
